Valeriia Cherepanova

∨cherepa@umd.edu | Google Scholar

Interests_

My research goal is to develop reliable, robust, and fair machine learning systems, which can be safely and effectively used for practical applications. I am also interested in advancing our understanding of how deep neural networks function and their failure modes.

Education .

University of Maryland, College Park

College Park

PhD in Applied Mathematics

Aug 2018 - Aug 2023

- Advisor: Prof. Tom Goldstein
- Dean's Fellowship

University College London

London

MSc in Modeling Biological Complexity (CoMPLEX)

Sept 2017 - Sept 2018

Graduated with distinction

National Research University Higher School of Economics

Moscow

BSc in Mathematics Sept 2013 - June 2017

Industry Experience

Amazon, Alexa Entertainment

Seattle

APPLIED SCIENTIST INTERN

Jun 2022 - Aug 2022

- Developed ML solutions to classify different types of Alexa mistakes for improving Alexa Voice Search on FireTV.
- Built ML models for predicting popularity of FireTV Voice Searches from time-series data.

Amazon, Alexa Monitoring

Bellevue

APPLIED SCIENTIST INTERN

Jun 2021 - Aug 2021

Jul 2016 - Oct 2016

- Developed NLP solutions to improve transparency of 3P Alexa Skills through detecting incompliant privacy policy documents.
- Deployed the model in production and built an interactive dashboard.

Teradata Moscow

DATA SCIENTIST INTERN

• Designed a machine learning training course for engineers at the company.

Selected Publications _

LowKey: Leveraging Adversarial Attacks to Protect Social Media Users from Facial Recognition

V. Cherepanova, M. Goldblum, H. Foley, S. Duan, J. P. Dickerson, G. Taylor, T. Goldstein *International Conference on Learning Representations (ICLR)*, 2021, [paper], [webtool]

Transfer Learning with Deep Tabular Models

R. Levin*, **V. Cherepanova***, A. Schwarzschild, A. Bansal, C. B. Bruss, T. Goldstein, A. G. Wilson, M. Goldblum *International Conference on Learning Representations (ICLR)*, 2023, [paper], [GitHub]

Strong Data Augmentation Sanitizes Poisoning and Backdoor Attacks Without an Accuracy Tradeoff

E. Borgnia*, **V. Cherepanova***, L. Fowl*, A. Ghiasi*, J. Geiping*, M. Goldblum*, T. Goldstein*, A. Gupta* *The International Conference on Acoustics*, *Speech*, & *Signal Processing (ICASSP)*, 2021, [paper]

A Deep Dive into Dataset Imbalance and Bias in Face Identification

V. Cherepanova*, S. Reich*, S. Dooley, H. Souri, M. Goldblum, T. Goldstein *AAAI/ACM Conference on AI, Ethics, and Society, 2023 [paper]*

Technical Challenges for Training Fair Neural Networks

V. Cherepanova*, V. Nanda*, M. Goldblum, J. P Dickerson, T. Goldstein

RAI Workshop at the International Conference on Learning Representations (ICLR), 2021, [paper]

Unraveling Meta-Learning: Understanding Feature Representations for Few-Shot Tasks

M. Goldblum, S. Reich*, L. Fowl*, R. Ni*, **V. Cherepanova***, T. Goldstein *International Conference on Machine Learning (ICML)*, 2020, [paper]

MetaBalance: High-Performance Neural Networks for Class-Imbalanced Data

A. Bansal, M. Goldblum, **V. Cherepanova**, A. Schwarzschild, C. B. Bruss, T. Goldstein *arXiv preprint*, [paper]

Comparing human and machine bias in face recognition

S. Dooley, R. Downing, G. Wei, N. Shankar, B. Thymes, G. Thorkelsdottir, T. Kurtz-Miott, R. Mattson, O. Obiwumi, **V. Cherepanova**, M. Goldblum, J.P. Dickerson, T. Goldstein *arXiv preprint*, [paper]

DP-InstaHide: Provably Defusing Poisoning and Backdoor Attacks with Differentially Private Data Augmentations E. Borgnia, J. Geiping, **V. Cherepanova**, L. Fowl, A. Gupta, A. Ghiasi, F. Huang, M. Goldblum, T. Goldstein

arXiv preprint, [paper]

\sim	r			
(An	ferences	วทศ	ובו	LC
COIL	ICICIICCO	anu	ıαι	rvs

Transfer Learning with Deep Tabular Models

- Oral Presentation at the NeurIPS 2022 Table Representation Learning Workshop
- Invited Talk at Arthur AI

A Deep Dive into Dataset Imbalance and Bias in Face Identification

- NeurIPS 2022 Workshop on Trustworthy and Socially Responsible Machine Learning
- NeurIPS 2022 Workshop on Algorithmic Fairness through the Lens of Causality and Privacy
- NeurIPS 2022 Workshop on Machine Learning Safety

Technical Challenges for Training Fair Neural Networks

ICLR 2021 Workshop on Responsible AI

LowKey: Leveraging Adversarial Attacks to Protect Social Media Users from Facial Recognition

- ICLR 2021
- NeurIPS 2020 Resistance AI Workshop
- NeurIPS 2020 Workshop on Dataset Curation and Security

Reviewer Service_		

ICML2023, NeurIPS 2022, ICLR 2022, NeurIPS 2021, NeurIPS 2022 TSRML Workshop, ICLR 2021 RAI Workshop, IEEE TPAMI

Relevant Coursework

Machine Learning: Deep Learning, Computer Vision, Computational Linguistics, Algorithms in Machine Learning: Guarantees and Convergence, Foundations of Deep Learning

Signal Processing: Scientific Computing, Advanced Numerical Optimization, Mathematical Statistics, Probability Theory, Applied Stochastic Processes

Technical Skills	

Programming: Python (PyTorch, PySpark, Huggingface, scikit-learn), SQL

^{*} indicates equal contribution